Guide to the Bob Witz Papers, circa early 1960s-2010 MSS.080
Fales Library and Special Collections
Bob Witz Papers
early 1960s-2010
Fales Library and Special Collections
Witz, Bob
MSS.080
6.5 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons, 2 flat boxes, 2 manuscript boxes, 7 oversize folders
Bob Witz is the editor of Appearances Magazine, a small arts magazine first published in the East Village during the 1980s. Witz is also an artist, writer and sculptor who lives in New York. The collection consists of material related to Appearances Magazine, correspondence, gallery catalogues and ephemera, sketchbooks, writings, chap books, drawings, and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Bob Witz Papers were donated to the Fales Library by Mr. Witz in the Fall of 1996. The accession number associated with the original donation is 1996.080. Multiple accretions to the collection were donated between 1997 and circa 2010. The accession numbers associated with these accretions are: 2001.080, 2006.080, 2009.080, 2014.080, 2015.080, 2017.049, 2017.050, 2017.051, 2017.052, 2017.053.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers.
Biographical Note
Bob Witz is a painter/sculptor, writer, poet, and editor of Appearances Magazine. Appearances is a small, low-budget magazine which was started in the East Village and has been published from the 1980s to the present. It is devoted mostly to the art scene with a focus on the alternative currents of this scene. Witz also published/produced small chapbooks, including an early book by Keith Haring, and Leaves of Grass II: a book/by Bob Witz (1972). Witz, along other writers represented in the Downtown collection (Ron Kolm and Tom Savage, 1948- ), is also closely associated with the Unbearables literary group.
Scope and Contents
The Bob Witz Papers/Appearances Magazine Collection (MSS 080) consists of material related to Appearances Magazine, correspondence, gallery catalogues and ephemera, sketchbooks, writings, chap books, drawings, and photographs.
Material related to Appearances Magazine includes notebooks compiled by Witz over his years as publisher of the magazine. Included within the notebooks are poems, drawings, phone numbers, and other assorted items. Other material related to the magazine include some financial and business records, submissions of writing and artwork, production files, and Appearances Press publications.
The collection also contains other materials collected by Witz including writings of his own and others, and additional notebooks, some from before the beginning of the magazine, and sketchbooks.
The collection includes both professional and personal correspondence. Among the correspondence are numerous exhibition announcements from various galleries around New York City and elsewhere. In addition to gallery ephemera there are also some exhibition catalogs from various galleries.
Arrangement
The original donation and 2009 accretion have been arranged into three series: Appearances, Correspondence, and Miscellaneous.
Other accretions to the collections have been added as separate series. The materials in these accretions are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Related Material at the Fales Library and Special Collections
Ron Kolm Papers, MSS 079
Separated Material
Items written by Witz (Leaves of Grass II, Berserker, and the Unbearable Manual of Style) are available to view at the Fales Library.
Avant-garde (Aesthetics) -- United States -- History -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; Literature, Modern -- 20th century -- Periodicals.; New York (N.Y.).; Literature, Experimental.; Small presses -- New York (State) -- New York.; Printed ephemera.; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life -- 20th century.; Manuscripts for publication.; Correspondence.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Scripts (documents); Drawings (visual works); Notes.; Business records.; Literature, Modern -- 20th century.; Sketchbooks.; Anthony, William; Spiegelman, Art; Cardin, Jörga; Appearances (Firm); Tisa, Ken, 1945-; Zummer, Thomas; Isaac, Jeffrey; Madore, Michael; Sandlin, David, 1956-
- Series I: Appearances
  Scope and Contents note
  The series consists primarily of notebooks compiled by Witz over his years as publisher of the magazine. Included within the notebooks are poems, drawings, phone numbers, and other assorted items. Also included in the series are financial documents and artwork from the magazine, as well as notebooks from before the beginning of the magazine.
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #1 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #1 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #1 & 2 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #2 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #3 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #3 & 4 - ca., 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #4 - ca., 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #5 & 6 ca., 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #8 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #8 & 9 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #9 & 10 ca., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #10 - Layout-ca., 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #11, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #11 Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #12, 13, 14 and Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #13 Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #13 Show - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #13 Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #14 Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #15 Ads; Show - Speed Limit 55 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #16 Ads - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Appearances Notebook - Issue #14, 15, 16 - n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notebook -, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Notebook - ca., 1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Notebook -, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notebook - ca., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appearances - ca., 1981? (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Appearances - ca., 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Show - Neo P. -, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebook -, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Appearances - Financial -, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Loose Artwork, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Appearances full page ad - layout, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Appearances - submissions, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series II: Correspondence
  The series consists of correspondence between Witz and others, both personal and professional. Organization is alphabetical.
  - Correspondence - A-F -, 1980-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - G-N -, 1980-1988, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - O-W -, 1982-1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - Unidentified -, 1984-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series III: Miscellaneous
  The series contains other materials collected by Witz including writings of his own and others, and additional notebooks apparently unrelated to Appearances.
  - Writings - Alan Ginsberg... -, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Writings - Leaves of Grass II -, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Writings - Quixote 10-Jul - ca., 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Publications by Others-Abstractions Per Se -, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Publications by Others - I read it... -, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Publications by Others - Quixote 2-Jun -, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Publications by Others - Quixote 3-Jun - n.d., undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Publications by Others - Quixote 6-Jun - n.d., undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Publications by Others - Quixote 8-Oct -, 1976? (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 3 Small Spiral notebooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 1 Large Spiral notebook, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Black Bound notebook, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Red Bound Notebook (1), 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Red Bound Notebook (2), Undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Accretion 2009 - Series I: Appearances
  - Appearances - gallery / artist cards and flyers, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Concurrent - exhibition brochure, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Accretion 2009 - Series II: Correspondence
  - Letters and cards, 2008-2009; undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Accretion 2009 - Series III: Miscellaneous
  - American Legion Junior Baseball Certificate of Eligibility, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Series IV: 1997 Accretion, early 1960s-2008
  Scope and Contents
  This accretion contains Bob Witz's sketchbooks (1974-1997), Stencil Novel (1978-1980), chapbooks (undated), submissions to Appearances Magazine, photographs, correspondence (1983-1997), newspapers (1970-1972), catalogues and ephemera from galleries (1983-1997). The accretion includes notes and writings by Bobby Joe Burbridge (late 1960s - early 1970s), and writing by Julie Gross.
  - Sketchbooks, Chapbooks, Photographs, Correspondence, Newspapers; Notes and Writings by Bobby Joe Burbridge, D.A. Levy and Julie Gross; Gallery Catalogues and Ephemera, Early 1960s-2008 (Box 4)
  - Sketchbooks, Photographs, Gallery Catalogues, Stencil Novel 1-4, and Beriah Wall Clay Tokens, 1977-2007 (Box 5)
  - Stencil Novel 5-15, Correspondence, Ephemera, and Sketches, 1979-1989 (Box 6)
- Series V: 2005 Accretion, 1986-2005
  This accretion contains a copy of Paul Lamarre's EIDIA Manifesto printed on a napkin, Appearances Magazine correspondence, including catalogues and gallery ephemera (1986-2005), and personal correspondence (1988-1990).
  - Correspondence, Gallery Catalogues and Ephemera, 1986-2005 (Box 7)
- Series VI: 2007 Accretion, Sketchbook, undated
  This accretion contains Bob Witz's sketchbook (undated).
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 14)
- Series VII: 2008 Accretion, late 1960s-2008
  This accretion contains Bob Witz's drawings and sketchbooks (undated), correspondence including gallery catalogues and ephemera (1974-2008), press releases and writing by Witz (1989-1992).
  - Sketchbooks, Chapbooks, Photographs, Correspondence, Newspapers; Notes and Writings by Bobby Joe Burbridge, D.A. Levy and Julie Gross; Gallery Catalogues and Ephemera, late 1960s-2008 (Box 4)
  - Sketchbooks, Photographs, Gallery Catalogues, Stencil Novel 1-4, and Beriah Wall Clay Tokens, 1977-2007 (Box 5)
  - Drawings, Correspondence, and Printed Ephemera, 1981-1989 (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook, undated (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 11)
  - Sketches and Printed Ephemera, 1960-75, 1997; -1997 (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 12)
- Series VIII: Undated Accretion(s), 1977-2010
  This accretion contains professional and personal correspondence (1977-2008), gallery catalogues and ephemera (1977-2008), submissions of writing and photographs to Appearances Magazine (undated, 1982, 1999, 2002-2010) and some Appearances production files, Appearances Press publications (1981-1986), a typescript of Don't Wait; Or, Wait, a novel by Robert Witz (undated), Bob Witz's sketchbooks (undated, 1990-2013) and some business records (circa 1980-1986) including Appearances certificate of incorporation (1983) and a list of subscribers (undated). There are also seven small flat round objects (1980s).
  - Photographs and Printed Epemera, undated (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 7)
  - Brooklyn Rail Magazine, June 2010 (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 8)
  - Shotsie Gorman Photographs and Printed Ephemera, undated (Box Shared Fales 003, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbooks, Photographs, Gallery Catalogues, Stencil Novel 1-4, and Beriah Wall Clay Tokens, 1977-2007 (Box 5)
  - Sketchbooks, Gallery Catalogues and Ephemera, Notebooks, Newspapers, Correspondence, Poetry Books, Photographs, and Submissions to Appearance Magazine, 1985-2013 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, Submissions to Appearance Magazine, Manuscripts, Gallery Catalogues and Ephemera, Books, and Photographs, 1996-2006 (Box 9)
- Series IX: 2001 Accretion, 1984-2002
  This accretion contains Bob Witz's financial records, correspondence, exhibition and performance announcements and submissions to Appearances Magazine.
  - Financial Records, Correspondence, Exhibition/Performance Announcements, and Submissions to Appearance Magazine, 1984-2002 (Box 10)
- Series X: 2014 Accretion, 1990-2014
  This accretion contains correspondence (2014), exhibition announcements (1990-2014), and gallery catalogues (2000-2014) particularly of Beatrice Caracciolo exhibitions.
  - Correspondence, Exhibition/Performance Announcements, and Gallery Catalogues, 1990-2014 (Box 11)